Guide to the Irah Chase Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Irah Chase Papers
1814-1864
RG 296
Yale University Divinity School Library
3
(7 boxes)
The collection documents Chase's theological training and his work at Columbian College and the Newton Theological Institution where he taught Biblical theology (1825-1838) and church history (1838-1845), as well as his later work as an author of tracts and articles for religious periodicals.
Biographical / Historical
Irah Chase was born in Stratton, Vermont, in 1793, and spent his childhood in that state. He graduated from Middlebury College in 1814, and from Andover Theological Seminary in 1817. After a year of service as a missionary in Virginia, he became associated with a Baptist ministerial training school in Philadelphia. Chase continued his association with that school when, in 1822, it was transferred to Washington, DC, as the theological department of Columbian College (now Georgetown University). In 1825 he moved to Massachusetts to inaugurate the course of study at Newton Theological Institution. At Newton he taught Biblical theology (1825-1838) and church history (1838-1845). After 1845 he engaged in literary work, and published several tracts and articles for religious periodicals. He died in Newton in 1864.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from Andover Newton Theological School to the Yale Divinity Library in 2017.
Scope and Contents
The Irah Chase Papers, 1814-1864, primarily document the professional work of Chase. The collection is arranged according to the following categories: correspondence, sermons, addresses, lectures, unpublished literary manuscripts, publications, student lecture notes from Andover Theological Seminary, notes on readings, notes on sermons, miscellaneous papers and reports. Included in the correspondence are several letters which relate to early Baptist educational work in general and to the ministerial training school in Philadelphia and Washington in particular. The sermon notes were transcribed during his student days at Andover, and provide a record of chapel sermons not available elsewhere. The miscellaneous papers primarily relate to Baptist educational work in the early 19th century.
Also included is a small number of items related to Cummings family genealogy, collected by William Leverett Cummings, a descendant of Henry Savage Chase, son of Irah and Harriet Savage, as well as an addendum contain photographs of the Middle East and additional correspondence and writings.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into eight series:
Series I. Correspondence
Series II. Sermons
Series III. Addresses and Lectures
Series IV. Unpublished Literary Manuscripts
Series V. Publications
Series VI. Notes
Series VII. Miscellaneous Papers and Reports
Series VIII. Addendum
- Correspondence, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  For a more detailed listing of correspondence, see original finding aid, which is linked to from https://web.library.yale.edu/divinity/special-collections/andover-newton.
  - Joseph Grafton to IC, No date (Box 1)
  - IC to editors of Reflector and Watchman, No date (Box 1)
  - IC to editors of Christian Chronicle, No date (Box 1)
  - IC to a minister, author of an article in Christian Chronicle, No date (Box 1)
  - IC to Rev. Luther Rice, 1815 (Box 1)
  - IC to Rev. Thomas Baldwin, 1818 (Box 1)
  - IC to Rev. Thomas Baldwin; to Rev. William Staughton, 1819 (Box 1)
  - IC to Rev. Thomas Baldwln; to "my dear sister", 1820 (Box 1)
  - IC to Rev. Thomas Baldwin; to/from Rev. D. B. Brown; to Dr. Staughton, 1821 (Box 1)
  - IC to Rev. Thomas Baldwin; to Rev. Luther Rice, 1822 (Box 1)
  - Trustees of Columbian College to IC; Dr. Staughton to IC, 1823 (Box 1)
  - IC to Dr. Sewall; to "my very dear brother"; to Herr Diaconus Hesekiel; to [P] Potts; to Rev. J. H. Hinton; to Dr. Baldwin, 1824 (Box 1)
  - IC and H. J. Ripley to Rev. E. Nelson (included is undated letter of IC to Rev. E. Nelson), 1826 (Box 1)
  - IC and Henry Ripley to Rev. Henry Jackson and Rev. James D. Knowles, 1827 (Box 1)
  - IC and H. J. Ripley to editor of Christian Watchman, 1828 (Box 1)
  - Including L. Wayland to IC; IC to whom it may concern, re Joel Smith Bacon, 1830 (Box 1)
  - Including Rev. Peter Chase to IC; IC to President Bates, 1832 (Box 1)
  - IC to Samuel B. Swain, 1833 (Box 1)
  - IC to President of Board of Trustees; to Albert Day, Henry Burgess and James Burt; to Nicholas Brown, 1836 (Box 1)
  - Silas Ilsley to IC, 1837 (Box 1)
  - Summary of a letter "in reply to inquiries made by a dear brother", 1839 (Box 1)
  - Rev. Dr. Dagg to IC, 1844 (Box 1)
  - IC to dear sir, 1848 (Box 1)
  - Charles Sumner to IC, 1853 (Box 1)
  - IC to Brother Henry, 1855 (Box 1)
  - W. B. Hackett to IC, 1856 (Box 1)
  - IC to Rev. Dr. Wood, 1858 (Box 1)
  - IC to Rev. Dr. Huntington, 1860 (Box 1)
  - IC to Rev. James Chrystal; to Rev. and dear sir, 1861 (Box 1)
  - IC to son; to Rev. Dr. Hansel, 1864 (Box 1)
- Sermons, Series II
  - Undated sermons arranged by text: Genesis - 2 Timothy (Box 1)
    For a full listing of scriptural texts, see original finding, which is linked to from https://web.library.yale.edu/divinity/special-collections/andover-newton.
  - Undated sermons arranged by text: Hebrews - Revelation (Box 2)
  - Dated sermons, 1818–1846 (Box 2)
    For a full listing of exact dates and scriptural texts see original finding aid, which is linked to from https://web.library.yale.edu/divinity/special-collections/andover-newton.
- Addresses and Lectures, Series III
  - Untitled addresses (6), No date (Box 2)
  - Communion meditation, No date (Box 2)
  - Address to graduating class, No date (Box 2)
  - Farewell to colleagues [Columbian College], No date (Box 2)
  - How a theological student is to prosecute his studies, No date (Box 2)
  - Address to a class by the Senior Professor at the anniversary, 1830 (Box 2)
  - Undated charges, No date (Box 2)
  - Charge to Jonathan Price, on his designation as a missionary to Burma, 1821 (Box 2)
  - Charge to to Isaac M. Willmarth, 1834 (Box 2)
  - Charge at the installation of Rev. Mr. Nott; at the ordination of Rev.Prof. Hackett, 1839 (Box 2)
  - Lectures: Bible (Box 2)
  - Lectures: Theology (Box 2)
  - Lectures: Church History (Box 2)
  - Lectures: Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Lecture notes: Theology (Box 2)
  - Lecture notes: Theology (Box 3)
  - Lecture notes: Church history (Box 3)
- Unpublished Literary Manuscripts, Series IV
  - Untitled (4) (Box 3)
  - Acts 8:37 (Box 3)
  - The acts of Pilate (Box 3)
  - The announcement which Jesus made of himself as the Messiah (Box 3)
  - Articles of Christian doctrine (Box 3)
  - Baptismal tracts for the times (Box 3)
  - The canons of the apostles (Box 3)
  - Dr. Hackett's revision of the Epistle to Philemon (Box 3)
  - Editorial comment (2) (Box 3)
  - The meaning of Irenaeus (Box 3)
  - The miracles of Christ (Box 3)
  - Remarks on the personality and divinity of the holy ghost (Box 3)
  - The savior's prospective arrangements (Box 3)
- Publications, Series V
  - Book
    - Infant Baptism an Invention of Men; or Dr. Bushnell's Arguments Reviewed. Philadelphia: American Baptist Publication Society, 1883. (Box 4)
      Incomplete manuscript, missing most of section 2 on "The testimony of Origen respecting the baptism of infants."
  - Articles
    - incomplete fragments (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - The baptism of Basil the Great: was it in his infancy? (Box 4)
    - Basil the Great, an important witness respecting baptism in the fourth century (Box 4)
    - Dr. Robinson and Dr. Ripley (Box 4)
    - Faith and works (Box 4)
    - The meaning of Irenaeus in the phrase, "regenerated unto God" (Box 4)
    - Gesenius' Hebrew Grammar (Box 4)
    - Neander (Box 4)
    - The new reformation in Germany (Box 4)
    - Our duty, in view of man's increasing dominion over nature (Box 4)
    - Principles of exposition (Box 4)
    - Punishment in the future state (2) (Box 4)
    - [Review of] A commentary on the epistle to the Hebrews by Moses Stuart (Box 4)
    - Review of Fuller on Communion (Box 4)
    - The spirit of the Mohammedan religions perceptible preeminently in the traditions (Box 4)
    - Tholuck (Box 4)
    - Unfounded claims to spiritual illuminations (3 drafts) (Box 4)
    - A voice from the second century (Box 4)
    - Who is awake? (Box 4)
- Notes, Series VI
  - Student lecture notes
    Notes taken while Chase was a student at Andover Theological Seminary
    - Incomplete fragments and untitled (Box 4)
    - Psalm 49 (Box 4)
    - Hints on public prayer (Box 4)
    - The resurrection (Box 4)
    - Subjects in theology (Box 4)
    - Booklet/November 24, 1814-0ctober 16, 1816: Leonard Woods' lectures on theology, 1814–1816 (Box 4)
    - Booklet/January 3-February 7, 1815: Prefaces to the gospels, The doctrine of accommodation, Syllabus of Quintilian on the human voice (Box 4)
    - Booklet/November 14, 1815: Dick on Inspiration of the holy scriptures; 2nd year--Dr. Woods' department (Box 4)
    - Booklet/November 20, 1815: The immutability of God (Box 4)
  - Notes on readings
    - 12 folders of notes; first folderincludes list of books by subject (Box 5)
  - Notes on sermons
    - Including sermons by Holbrook, Parkhurst, Aiken, Fitch, Wilson, Stuart, Hooks, Taylor, Wright, Parsons, Calhoun, Stratton, Woods, Morse, Rockwood, Emerson, Harris, Ely, 1816–1817 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous notes
    - 8 folders of notes (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous Papers and Reports, Series VII
  - Reports and statements
    - Untitled, on theological education (Box 5)
    - Plan of a theological institution to be connected with Brown University. Recommended by the trustees of the Education Societies of the Warren and Boston Association, 1817 (Box 5)
    - Institution for pious young men called to the gospel ministry, Aug. 10, 1818 (incomplete) (Box 5)
    - A brief statement of what occurred in the Philadelphia Association, on Tuesday and Wednesday, the 6th and 7th of Oct. 1818, relative to the First Baptist Church in Philadelphia (Box 5)
    - Circular letter: The elders and messengers of the Fairfield Baptist Association, convened at Milton, on the 25th and 26th days of August, AD 1819, to the churches which they represent (Box 5)
    - Newton Theological Institution--Report on semi-annual examination, No date (Box 5)
    - Newton Theological Institution--Response to statements in the Watchman and Reflector on Dr. Hackett's absence, No date (Box 5)
    - Committee reports: On religious tracts; On missions; On missions to the Indians; On a memorial of Dr. Chapin (Box 5)
    - Report to the trustees of Newton Theological Institution on the subject of a preparatory department (incomplete) (Box 5)
    - Report to the executive committee of the Missionary Union on Gammel's History of the American Baptist Missions, 1849 (Box 5)
    - On the Book of Job (booklet in German script) (Box 5)
  - Publications on life of Irah Chase
    - "Rev. Irah Chase, D.D." In BAPTIST MEMORIAL & MONTHLY RECORD. ed. Rev. Enoch Hutchinson, 5-82. New York: Z.P. Hatch., 1850 (Box 5)
    - IN MEMORIUM, TRIBUTE OF AFFECTION TO THE MEMORY OF PROFESSOR IRAH CHASE. Boston: Geo. C. Rand & Avery, Printers, 1865 (Box 5)
    - CHRISTIAN GREATNESS IN THE SCHOLAR, A DISCOURSE ON THE LIFE AND CHARACTER OF REV. IRAH CHASE, D.D ... Delivered before the Society of Inquiry at Newton, June 27, 1865 by William Hague, D.D. Boston: Gould and Lincoln, 1866 (Box 5)
    - "Ira Chase, the Missionary, the Scholar and the Saint." in CHRISTIAN REPOSITORY AND HOME CIRCLE. ed. S.R. Ford, (August, 1884): 95-102 (Box 5)
  - Chase family papers
    - Cummings family genealogy - William Leverett Cummings descended from Henry Savage Chase, son of Irah and Harriet Savage (Box 5)
    - Letters: Ellen Chase, 1925 (Box 5)
- Addendum, Series VIII
  - Photographs of the Middle East (Box 6)
  - Correspondence and writings, 1834–1836 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1838–1843 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1847 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1854–1858 (Box 7)
  - Published writings: Bunsen's View of Baptism, 1853 (Box 7)
  - Published writings: The Design of Baptism Viewed in Its Relation to Christian Life, 1851 (Box 7)
  - Handwritten notes (Box 7)
  - Manuscripts, letters to editors (Box 7)
  - Manuscript: The Life of Bunyan (Box 7)
  - Manuscript: The Prayers for Infants in the Apostolical Constitutions (Box 7)